[SPEAKER_00]: We drove deeper and deeper into the bush.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lancia!
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah!
[SPEAKER_00]: What is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Looks like the sea.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eventually, the road disappeared altogether.
[SPEAKER_00]: People of Surrey, I hope you're watching this.
[SPEAKER_00]: We are...
[SPEAKER_00]: driving a Lancia Beta Coupe, well, just in the middle of the... whatever you call this.
[SPEAKER_00]: The good news was we'd successfully reached our campsite for the night.
[SPEAKER_00]: The bad news came in the shape of another challenge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stretching before you is the Mercati Caddy.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are the biggest salt flats in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're almost completely lifeless and as wide as Portugal.
[SPEAKER_00]: No car has ever driven across them.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you run out of water, you will die.
[SPEAKER_00]: If your car breaks down and you can't be rescued, you will die.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you run out of food, you will die.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like driving on a creme brulee.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a primeval ooze covered with a thin layer of salty crust.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have thin tyres, you will break through that crust, get stuck and you will die.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it advises to fit fat tyres and remove as much weight as possible before setting off.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, how hard can it be?
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't say that!
[SPEAKER_00]: In camp, the weight-shedding began.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ready?
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thanks awfully.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feel how much this seat weighs.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, you work.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fuel filler, I'll need that, maybe.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm going to take the hubcaps off, really, because they protect the hubs.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I point something out?
[SPEAKER_00]: What?
[SPEAKER_00]: Hammond's walking around his car muttering about how he needs all of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know exactly what he's doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's formed an emotional attachment, hasn't he?
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be like saying to him, could you cut bits off your wife?
[SPEAKER_00]: What are you doing?
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm just going to take the radiator grill off on the basis that it's just an ornament.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I help you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Please do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you want your windows there?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no, no, they're fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, really, I've worked that out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Glasses?
[SPEAKER_02]: This is the old glass.
[SPEAKER_02]: Very thin glass.
[SPEAKER_00]: Very thin.
[SPEAKER_00]: God, they come off easily.
[SPEAKER_00]: James?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes?
[SPEAKER_00]: Using nothing but a hammer?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Here's your beer.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, mate.
[SPEAKER_02]: Have we lost enough weight now?
[SPEAKER_00]: You haven't lost an ounce.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've lost the spare wheel and something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now look at mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm going to need some guide ropes to stop it floating away like a big balloon.
[SPEAKER_00]: So tomorrow we die then?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I think it's like all these things, it's exaggerated.
[SPEAKER_00]: We'll be fine, honestly.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're going to be fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: We've done enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: The next morning, on the edge of the salt pans, we thought we'd come under attack from a Bond villain, but it turned out to be the vice-president of Botswana.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is a killer ride.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's better than an official Rover 75 and a couple of policemen on motorbikes.
[SPEAKER_02]: He was amazed to hear what was being planned.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've just never known anybody to go across in a car.
[SPEAKER_02]: This should be the first time, I think.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, really?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: That should be interesting.
[SPEAKER_02]: You were smiling, you've just stopped.
[SPEAKER_02]: Buoyed by the Vice President's optimism, we set off.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing really prepares you for the sheer size of these.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think, in a way, that is more frightening than the pole.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's absolutely... You can see the curvature of the earth.
[SPEAKER_02]: As we ploughed on, the little Opel was going well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oliver is just skipping.
[SPEAKER_01]: Boom!
[SPEAKER_01]: This car was born to do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sadly, though, despite the weight-shedding, my Lancia was not doing so well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Judging by the way the tyres are kind of turning,