[SPEAKER_04]: Hello, hello, and welcome.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_05]: Now, as you know, the producers on this show like to give us challenges, specifically where they give us a very small amount of money and tell us to buy a used car.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then they set unbelievably hard tasks to do to see which one of us got the best deal.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: This week, for a Top Gear special, they came up with a real humdinger.
[SPEAKER_06]: They gave each of us 1,500 quid and told us to go to Africa and buy a car.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, there were just two conditions.
[SPEAKER_03]: It mustn't be four-wheel drive, and it mustn't be built in any way to go off-road.
[SPEAKER_03]: The meeting point was the border post between Zimbabwe and Botswana.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, for once, I was the first to arrive.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, as you'd expect, I've done this properly.
[SPEAKER_03]: What I've got is a 1985 Mercedes-Benz 230e, a car that Africa absolutely adores, because it's comfortable, it's rugged, it's dependable, and frankly, if the other two have brought anything other than one of these along, they're idiots.
[SPEAKER_03]: The first idiot arrived.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can you open the door?
[SPEAKER_03]: The handle's broken.
[SPEAKER_05]: It is a Lancia Beta.
[SPEAKER_05]: Coup, 1981.
[SPEAKER_05]: The only Lancia of any sort in the whole of Botswana.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's done 29,000 miles.
[SPEAKER_05]: One owner, is it?
[SPEAKER_05]: It's the little old lady.
[SPEAKER_05]: And boy, had she ragged it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's normal, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_03]: That fizzing?
[SPEAKER_03]: That's... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: What's the piece of cardboard for?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is that for mopping up moisture?
[SPEAKER_05]: No, that's because the battery... Oh, it shorts on the bonnet?
[SPEAKER_05]: Shorts on the bonnet a bit.
[SPEAKER_05]: You've done well.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, now what?
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you want a lift?
[SPEAKER_03]: We left the Lancia to cool down, because Hammond was arriving.
[SPEAKER_05]:  What the hell is that?
[SPEAKER_05]:  I don't know.
[SPEAKER_05]: Could it be a Moskvitch?
[SPEAKER_05]:  It's an Opel.
[SPEAKER_05]:  Opel?
[SPEAKER_05]: And on the front it says Cadet.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah!
[SPEAKER_06]: What the hell have you done, man?
[SPEAKER_06]: It's an Opel Cadet from 1963.
[SPEAKER_05]: So that's the same age as... That's the same age as Nick.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes, but it's much better Nick than you.
[SPEAKER_06]: It was 1,200.
[SPEAKER_06]: I had much change with which to buy many beans.
[SPEAKER_06]: How much more simple can you get?
[SPEAKER_06]: It's got two moving parts and it's been here for 44 years.
[SPEAKER_05]: I love the speedo.
[SPEAKER_05]: I do like a horizontal speedo.
[SPEAKER_03]: I really do.
[SPEAKER_03]: Where's the engine?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hang on.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's tiny.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you want to know about the power?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, I do.
[SPEAKER_03]: Forty.
[SPEAKER_06]: Forty horsepower.
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, they did do a sport version with 48, but I didn't want anything too lairy.
[SPEAKER_03]: You've both been idiots.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Brilliantly interesting, brilliantly stylish, but stupid.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is mine stupid?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where is yours?
[SPEAKER_06]: Anansi, you have been a bit thick.
[SPEAKER_05]: With the cars at the start line, it was time for our challenge.
[SPEAKER_05]: The people of Surrey think they need four-wheel drive cars because they live up a lane which sometimes has leaves on it.
[SPEAKER_05]: You will now attempt to prove them wrong by driving your two-wheel drive cars from here on Botswana's eastern border with Zimbabwe, which is there, 1,000 miles to its western border with Namibia.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's right across the spine of Africa.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm confident.
[SPEAKER_05]: I wasn't.
[SPEAKER_05]: We hadn't even started and the Lancia was playing up.
[SPEAKER_05]: James chose not to wait.
[SPEAKER_05]: He may be mechanically confident, but he has just turned right, which is symbolic, which is where I should point out the BBC is not allowed.
[SPEAKER_07]: Sorry, sorry.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm going now.
[SPEAKER_05]: The Lancia wheezed into life and Hammond and I set off in pursuit.
[SPEAKER_06]: If you think of the cars that this inspired, it was latterly built in Russia, where it became the Moskvich, which was rubbish.
[SPEAKER_06]: And, of course, indirectly, the Vauxhall Astra.
[SPEAKER_06]: Quite a lot of reasonably average cars owe themselves to this.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know if you know, but Africa is really quite large, and when you're out in a very remote part, you need a car like this that can be mended with a brick and a piece of string.
[SPEAKER_05]: What you have to remember is that three of the most rugged and successful rally cars ever made were Lancia's.
[SPEAKER_05]: The Stratos, the 037 and the Delta Integrale.
[SPEAKER_05]: Lancia know how to make a rally car.
[SPEAKER_05]: Unfortunately, on the day my beaut coup was made, they obviously forgot everything.
[SPEAKER_05]: The gearbox is broken, the steering's broken, the window's broken.
[SPEAKER_05]: In fact, we all had problems.
[SPEAKER_03]: Everything works except this knob, which controls the blood.
[SPEAKER_03]: I've got to have the windows open because there's quite a strong smell of petrol.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that mirror over there, which is actually slightly stuck.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hazard warning lights, the clock, the fan, the handbrake, all of the dials.
[SPEAKER_06]: The brakes are terrible because they only work on that wheel.
[SPEAKER_06]: They work very well on that wheel, but only on that wheel.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that instrument's a bit wobbly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Apart from that, everything that's actually important to the car works perfectly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Apart from the handbrake, which I can pull like this as we go along.
[SPEAKER_05]: Nevertheless, because we were on tarmac roads, we decided to give our cars a shakedown.
[SPEAKER_05]: Building up speed now.
[SPEAKER_05]: When it was made, this car had 116 horsepower.
[SPEAKER_05]: Top speed, 115 miles an hour.
[SPEAKER_05]: Here we go.
[SPEAKER_05]: Going 100 kilometres an hour more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, I'm going to overtake the truck.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here I go.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's pulled out of its slipstream.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's really coming up.
105.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still truck.
[SPEAKER_03]: 3,000 revs, 3,500.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pulls cleanly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hang on a minute.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's got no fifth gear.
[SPEAKER_03]: Somebody's put the knob from a five-gear model on it.
[SPEAKER_08]: This is just the happiest car in the world.
[SPEAKER_06]: As we call it, Oliver.
[SPEAKER_06]: Not that we'd ever name a car on top of it.
[SPEAKER_06]: I wish I hadn't said that.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's now five past ten in the morning and it's starting to get quite hot.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've got an idea.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's better.
[SPEAKER_06]: Don't know what that is.
[SPEAKER_08]: The horn!
[SPEAKER_08]: Oliver, you've got a cold!
[SPEAKER_08]: Listen!
[SPEAKER_06]: We were having fun, but then we discovered we were travelling with Bill Oddie.
[SPEAKER_05]: Why have you got a pen?
[SPEAKER_05]: You tick them off when you've seen them.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hornbill, southern yellowbill.
[SPEAKER_06]: Take a look at your car.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's massive!
[SPEAKER_06]: Don't knock Oliver.
[SPEAKER_06]: Don't knock my car.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's a fine... He's a fine... What did you call it, then?
[SPEAKER_06]: Oliver's a friend of mine and I thought you were talking about him.
[SPEAKER_06]: He's given it a name.
[SPEAKER_06]: He's given his car a name.
[SPEAKER_05]: So far, the journey had been a doddle.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then the tarmac just sort of stopped.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, this is bad.
[SPEAKER_03]: I can see from here just how hard the suspension on Jeremy's Lance is having to work.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just a blur.
[SPEAKER_08]: Come on, Oliver, please!
[SPEAKER_03]: The later you book a lift in the Mercedes, the more expensive it gets.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a bit like an airline.
[SPEAKER_08]: Oh, God!
[SPEAKER_08]: Oh!
[SPEAKER_03]: Engine isn't working, it's cut out.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, dear.
[SPEAKER_05]: He's done literally one kilometre of this.
[SPEAKER_05]: I know what's wrong with it.
[SPEAKER_05]: The bonnet won't open.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, it's the bonnet catch.
[SPEAKER_05]: Shut up!
[SPEAKER_05]: Hammond was tetchy because he knew the price of failure.
[SPEAKER_05]: Anyone whose car broke down would have to complete the journey in a beetle.
[SPEAKER_05]: It is collectively our least favourite car in the world.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: It is the punishment.
[SPEAKER_05]: Please!
[SPEAKER_08]: Oh, hang on, hang on!
Oh!
[SPEAKER_05]: Come on, Oliver!
[SPEAKER_05]: What did you say?
[SPEAKER_08]: I said, I love you!
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, my God.
[SPEAKER_05]: What now?
[SPEAKER_05]: My car's on fire, but in a very specific place.
[SPEAKER_05]: Wow, look at that.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a magnifying glass.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a laser beam coming through it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, his piece of cardboard's gone.
[SPEAKER_06]: So it sets itself on fire?
[SPEAKER_05]: If you don't have a piece of cardboard.
[SPEAKER_05]: We drove deeper and deeper into the bush.
[SPEAKER_05]: Lancia!
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah!
[SPEAKER_05]: What is that?
[SPEAKER_05]: Looks like the sea.
[SPEAKER_05]: Eventually, the road disappeared altogether.
[SPEAKER_05]: People of Surrey, I hope you're watching this.
[SPEAKER_05]: We are... I'm driving a Lancia Beta Coupe, well, just in the middle of the... whatever you call this.
[SPEAKER_05]: The good news was we'd successfully reached our campsite for the night.
[SPEAKER_05]: The bad news came in the shape of another challenge.
[SPEAKER_05]: Stretching before you is the macadicaddy.
[SPEAKER_05]: These are the biggest salt flats in the world.
[SPEAKER_05]: They're almost completely lifeless and as wide as Portugal.
[SPEAKER_05]: No car has ever driven across them.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you run out of water, you will die.
[SPEAKER_05]: If your car breaks down and you can't be rescued, you will die.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you run out of food, you will die.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like driving on a creme brulee.
[SPEAKER_05]: There's a primeval ooze covered with a thin layer of salty crust.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you have thin tyres, you will break through that crust, get stuck and you will die.
[SPEAKER_05]: So it advises to fit fat tyres and remove as much weight as possible before setting off.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, how hard can it be?
[SPEAKER_04]: Don't say that!
[SPEAKER_05]: In camp, the weight-shedding began.
[SPEAKER_05]: Ready?
[SPEAKER_05]: That doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thanks awfully.
[SPEAKER_03]: Feel how much this seat weighs.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right, you work.
[SPEAKER_07]: Fuel filler, I'll need that, maybe.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm going to take the hubcaps off, really, because they protect the hubs.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can I point something out?
[SPEAKER_03]: What?
[SPEAKER_03]: Hammond's walking around his car muttering about how he needs all of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know exactly what he's doing.
[SPEAKER_05]: He's formed an emotional attachment, hasn't he?
[SPEAKER_05]: It would be like saying to him, could you cut bits off your wife?
[SPEAKER_03]: What are you doing?
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm just going to take the radiator grill off on the basis that it's just an ornament.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can I help you?
[SPEAKER_03]: Please do.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you want your windows there?
[SPEAKER_06]: No, no, no, no, they're fine.
[SPEAKER_06]: No, really, I've worked that out.
[SPEAKER_04]: Glasses?
[SPEAKER_06]: This is the old glass.
[SPEAKER_06]: Very thin glass.
[SPEAKER_05]: Very thin.
[SPEAKER_05]: God, they come off easily.
[SPEAKER_05]: James?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes?
[SPEAKER_05]: Using nothing but a hammer?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Here's your beer.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you, mate.
[SPEAKER_06]: Have we lost enough weight now?
[SPEAKER_05]: You haven't lost an ounce.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've lost the spare wheel and something else.
[SPEAKER_05]: Now look at mine.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm going to need some guide ropes to stop it floating away like a big balloon.
[SPEAKER_03]: So tomorrow we die then?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, I think it's like all these things, it's exaggerated.
[SPEAKER_05]: We'll be fine.
[SPEAKER_05]: Honestly, we're going to be fine.
[SPEAKER_05]: We've done enough.
[SPEAKER_06]: The next morning, on the edge of the salt pans, we thought we'd come under attack from a Bond villain, but it turned out to be the vice-president of Botswana.
[SPEAKER_06]: That is a killer ride.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's better than an official Rover 75 and a couple of policemen on motorbikes.
[SPEAKER_06]: He was amazed to hear what was being planned.
[SPEAKER_06]: I've just never known anybody to go across in a car.
[SPEAKER_06]: This should be the first time, I think.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, really?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: That should be interesting.
[SPEAKER_06]: You were smiling, you've just stopped.
[SPEAKER_06]: Buoyed by the Vice President's optimism, we set off.
[SPEAKER_05]: Nothing really prepares you for the sheer size of these.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think, in a way, that is more frightening than the pole.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can see the curvature of the earth.
[SPEAKER_06]: As we ploughed on, the little Opel was going well.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oliver is just skipping.
[SPEAKER_06]: Boom!
[SPEAKER_06]: This car was born to do this.
[SPEAKER_05]: Sadly, though, despite the weight-shedding, my Lancia was not doing so well.
[SPEAKER_05]: Judging by the way the tyres are kind of digging in as I'm driving along, I think a little bit more has to come out.
[SPEAKER_05]: Still, as you can see from the tyres' grooves, I was doing better than the Merc.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm looking at James's rear wheel and he's digging in a long way.
[SPEAKER_05]: I tried to help him along.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's really helpful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, he's always the beetle, James.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's waiting for you.
[SPEAKER_08]: What are you going to do?
[SPEAKER_08]: It's sinking.
[SPEAKER_05]: Honestly, we've done... How far is that, a mile?
[SPEAKER_05]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_05]: My Lancia waded in again.
[SPEAKER_07]: Just a nudge.
[SPEAKER_07]: That's a crash.
[SPEAKER_05]: There's a thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: Unfortunately, because it was an automatic, it was useless.
[SPEAKER_05]: So we told Richard to try.
[SPEAKER_05]: But he didn't want to hurt Oliver.
[SPEAKER_05]: This was hopeless, so we had to rope in the camera crew.
[SPEAKER_05]: Three, two, one... Because the ooze was so bad, we had to get even more drastic with the weight-shedding.
[SPEAKER_05]: We toiled away for hours.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, two of us did.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, finally, we were ready.
[SPEAKER_05]: Now, this is light.
[SPEAKER_05]: Lancia, Beta, Coupe, Superleggera.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not a modification.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is excellent.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why don't all cars have no doors?
[SPEAKER_05]: When I come to power, I'm going to make it a rule, because this is just better.
[SPEAKER_05]: However, the Mercati Caddy was not going to let us off that lightly, and soon even our super lightweight cars started to struggle again.
[SPEAKER_05]: Come on, just... Oh.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: No, this isn't good.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, no.
[SPEAKER_06]: Only the Opel remained trouble-free, which was bad news for me.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes!
[SPEAKER_05]: Come on, man.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'll go forward, Sam, and then we'll do it again.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hang on.
[SPEAKER_08]: How far is it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Another five or six yards and we might be bobbing.
[SPEAKER_08]: Oh, this is just horrible.
[SPEAKER_08]: Keep going, keep going, keep going.
[SPEAKER_08]: Keep going.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes!
Yes!
[SPEAKER_05]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: James, don't go there.
[SPEAKER_05]: You'll get stuck.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's close.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, for goodness' sake.
[SPEAKER_05]: We have everybody, we'll push it off.
[SPEAKER_05]: We need 100 men or more.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is hopeless.
[SPEAKER_05]: People of Surrey, you need four-wheel drive for this bit.
[SPEAKER_05]: The gunk was so sticky, it had completely jammed the Lancia's rear wheels.
[SPEAKER_06]: I can't describe it.
[SPEAKER_06]: You just think it's just mud.
[SPEAKER_06]: Do you know what it is?
[SPEAKER_05]: Fish.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's just rotted, prehistoric fish.
[SPEAKER_05]: One, two, three.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mercifully, the ground eventually hardened and we made good progress.
[SPEAKER_05]: But then suddenly, the horizon was no longer flat.
[SPEAKER_06]: Now, this is interesting, because we're now coming between what look like islands.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I suppose they are.
[SPEAKER_06]: This was a lake, so they would have been islands.
[SPEAKER_06]: Amazing.
[SPEAKER_05]: Absolutely amazing.
[SPEAKER_04]: Where are we?
[SPEAKER_05]: It's called Kubu Island.
[SPEAKER_05]: We're about...
[SPEAKER_05]: A third of the way across.
[SPEAKER_06]: And you've been stuck about a thousand times.
[SPEAKER_05]: That is smug.
[SPEAKER_06]: A baobab tree.
[SPEAKER_06]: Always wanted to see one of those.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hammond, look at this.
[SPEAKER_05]: Whoa!
[SPEAKER_05]: It is just about the most astonishing place I've ever been.
[SPEAKER_07]: Kind of witty there.
[SPEAKER_05]: As the sun set, we headed for the campsite.
[SPEAKER_05]: Day two on the salt pans, and we'd been told that today our problem would not be mud, but dust.
[SPEAKER_05]: That meant James and I had to rethink our wardrobe solutions.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've teamed my koi with a bin liner.
[SPEAKER_05]: V-necked.
[SPEAKER_05]: The last time I wore one of these, I'd seen a clash.
[SPEAKER_05]: Frankly, I thought it was all a bit much.
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, how bad could this dust be?
[SPEAKER_04]: My eyes!
[SPEAKER_03]: Crikey, I can't even see Jezza already.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_06]: Meanwhile, in my unmodified cadet... I'm going to adjust my quarter light a bit.
[SPEAKER_06]: Just an inch.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's better.
[SPEAKER_06]: I can feel the heat there.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's nice.
[SPEAKER_03]: The kakai's come off.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hello?
[SPEAKER_05]: James and I made it through the dust with our lives considerably shortened.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've got consumption and TB.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've got every single 1920s disease.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then Lord Smug piped up.
[SPEAKER_06]: I had to close this at one point, just about that much, and then it pulls the air out and you just get fresh air through, it's nice.
[SPEAKER_05]: You know what it's like when someone punches you really hard in the middle of the face?
[SPEAKER_06]: I do, actually.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then the surface got even worse.
[SPEAKER_05]: It was like we were descending through the seven circles of hell.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'd assumed it'd be the salt that would kill the notoriously rust-prone Lancia, but it was the rough going.
[SPEAKER_05]: Even though it had now smoothed out again, the beater was in a bad way.
[SPEAKER_06]: I've gone.
[SPEAKER_06]: Are you conking out?
[SPEAKER_06]: I've got no power, no drive.
[SPEAKER_06]: Do you remember what the man said, Jeremy?
[SPEAKER_06]: Breakdown and you... What is it?
[SPEAKER_06]: Have a nice time?
[SPEAKER_06]: No, die.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, that's loose.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's hot.
[SPEAKER_05]: It is a good job they cantered this engine over by 20 degrees, because that means it's more inaccessible than it would otherwise have been.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, my God, look at this.
[SPEAKER_06]: I've got to say, it has been nice, the piece.
[SPEAKER_06]: You know, not having him around.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've checked the alternator, the spark plugs, the HT leads and the distributor cap.
[SPEAKER_05]: Poked around with the starter solenoid.
[SPEAKER_05]: There's been faults with all of them, but it still isn't going.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm not sure which I favour most here, certain death or that beetle.
Come off!
[SPEAKER_05]: I honestly believe it's had it.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's my car on the crab.
[SPEAKER_06]: No, it's tracking Troentruve.
[SPEAKER_06]: He's worried about tracking, and look at it.
[SPEAKER_06]: We knew that Jeremy would eventually catch us up, but what would he be driving?
[SPEAKER_06]: I can see something in the mirrors.
[SPEAKER_02]: Please let it be a beetle.
[SPEAKER_02]: I do hope it's a beetle.
[SPEAKER_08]: Please, please let it be a Beetle.
[SPEAKER_02]: Please let it be a Beetle.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm back!
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, Jeremy, well done.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm disappointed... Sorry, delighted.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're not in a Beetle!
[SPEAKER_04]: Not a Beetle.
[SPEAKER_04]: A fully functioning Lancia Beetle Coupe.
[SPEAKER_06]: I just wanted the Beetle to pounce on you when you were straying behind.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm gutted.
[SPEAKER_05]: Shall we just sandwich him, James?
[SPEAKER_04]: No!
[SPEAKER_06]: With our convoy back up to strength, we pressed on, apart from Jeremy being Bill Oddie occasionally.
[SPEAKER_05]: This is where flamingos breed out here.
[SPEAKER_05]: So that's breeding, is it?
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a fossil.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not a fossil.
[SPEAKER_05]: It only died about two years ago.
[SPEAKER_05]: I was talking about you.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's an ex-flamingo.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hey, no, look.
[SPEAKER_05]: What now?
[SPEAKER_05]: I know what created this.
[SPEAKER_05]: Ostrich.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes!
[SPEAKER_05]: Its legs are miles apart.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's exactly how it was walking.
[SPEAKER_05]: You know, David Attenborough's about to retire.
[SPEAKER_05]: Can I just say... What?
[SPEAKER_03]: You look like a gay cowboy and you look like a gay terrorist.
[SPEAKER_05]: No, you look like a terrorist with a broken windscreen wiper and your face is ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_05]: Ern Hammond started to pick on my car.
[SPEAKER_06]: Why haven't you turned it off?
[SPEAKER_05]: It's gathering electricity.
[SPEAKER_06]: So if you turn it off, the battery's not going to start it again.
[SPEAKER_06]: Turn it off and start it then.
[SPEAKER_05]: Turn it off and start it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Let's have some beautiful silence.
[SPEAKER_05]: Are you ready?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Behold...
[SPEAKER_04]: Why did you turn it off, you idiot?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because he said it would... Good luck, mate.
[SPEAKER_04]: Somebody will give you a jump start.
[SPEAKER_04]: It'll be fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: Don't go away.
[SPEAKER_04]: Goodbye.
[SPEAKER_03]: Annoyingly, Clarkson got the Lancia going again.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then we came across some big birds.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then we saw even more wildlife.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a cow.
[SPEAKER_03]: Two cows, three cows.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes!
[SPEAKER_04]: We've done it!
[SPEAKER_05]: We had crossed the Macaddy Caddy.
[SPEAKER_04]: Trees!
[SPEAKER_06]: Life!
[SPEAKER_06]: Mate, did you ever think that you'd do that?
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm genuinely proud of him.
[SPEAKER_06]: I am.
[SPEAKER_05]: Really, I'm startled that this, that isn't a car anymore, whatever it is, has done it.
[SPEAKER_05]: with its low-profile tyres and its low suspension that's broken.
[SPEAKER_03]: Personally, I'm absolutely delighted because I think the Macaddy Caddy is one of the most unpleasant places I've ever been.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just a big bowl of dust.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hello, mate.
[SPEAKER_05]: Widow Twankey may have been glad to see the back of the salt pans, but despite this, they gave us a startling parting gift.
[SPEAKER_05]: Wow, that is amazing.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's the moon.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, that's the moon.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because of the dust from the pans, you get... A moonrise in orange.
[SPEAKER_07]: I've got goosebumps.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know a Philip Larkin poem about the moon.
[SPEAKER_03]: Would you like to hear it?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: As a new day dawned, our cars looked like wrecks.
[SPEAKER_05]: But their ordeal was far from over.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, we had crossed the salt pans, but we were still only a third of the way across Botswana.
[SPEAKER_05]: And now we were about to enter the Kalahari.
[SPEAKER_05]: Kalahari.
[SPEAKER_05]: Everyone who comes to the Kalahari takes away a different memory of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Savagery, the simplicity, the vast heat.
[SPEAKER_05]: Me, I think bumpiness.
[SPEAKER_05]: It was as rough as hell, so we were glad when news came through that we were to stop at the next village.
[SPEAKER_06]: Obviously, they recognise a truly classy car.
[SPEAKER_05]: What could they possibly have in mind for us here?
[SPEAKER_05]: It was another challenge.
[SPEAKER_07]: Hello.
[SPEAKER_05]: Here it is.
[SPEAKER_05]: Your cars have travelled far and suffered much.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, they have.
[SPEAKER_05]: So we will now discover how much performance they've lost in a competition against the clock on a rally special stage.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mine can't have lost any performance.
[SPEAKER_03]: It never added any.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I'm not going to ruin my Mercedes just for a few points.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're right, you're not, because you're not driving it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, who is?
[SPEAKER_05]: Some say he's seen the Lion King 1,780 times, and that his second best friend is a Cape buffalo.
[SPEAKER_05]: All we know is he's not the Stig, but he is the Stig's African cousin.
[SPEAKER_05]: He's protecting the important bits.
[SPEAKER_06]: Keen to get going, the three of us fired up our engines.
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, when I say three.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's absolutely dead.
[SPEAKER_05]: Nothing is functioning.
[SPEAKER_05]: There is no electrical... You two are not being helpful.
[SPEAKER_05]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: What a stupid thing to say.
[SPEAKER_05]: Interior light, headlight?
[SPEAKER_05]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_05]: You don't know how to mend the ignition circuit on a 1981 Lancia Beetle?
[SPEAKER_05]: No, it's... It was a long shot.
[SPEAKER_06]: Annoyingly, a couple of the locals did know what to do.
[SPEAKER_06]: And we drove to African Stig's rally stage, which was in a dried-up riverbed a few miles away.
[SPEAKER_06]: With packed spectator stands, Oliver went first.
[SPEAKER_06]: Three, two...
[SPEAKER_06]: One.
[SPEAKER_06]: Go!
[SPEAKER_06]: Three miles an hour.
[SPEAKER_06]: You know, when it was new, it had 40 horsepower.
[SPEAKER_05]: If it's lost one a year, it's at minus four.
[SPEAKER_05]: He's going round the first corner.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_05]: That was a power slide.
[SPEAKER_05]: Look at that.
[SPEAKER_05]: It does look... Ridiculous is the word you're looking for.
[SPEAKER_05]: As the cadets struggle to get up the hill, the spectators left.
[SPEAKER_06]: It is eminent.
[SPEAKER_06]: Come on, joggle it, Stig's cousin.
[SPEAKER_06]: He's enjoying that.
[SPEAKER_06]: And one minute, 12 seconds.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think that's a good benchmark for you to try and beat.
[SPEAKER_03]: Next up was the Panzer Tank.
[SPEAKER_03]: Most powerful, longest, best tyres... Longest?
[SPEAKER_05]: Longest is good for rallying, is it?
[SPEAKER_05]: It is on this, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So why doesn't... On loose surface rallies, don't they turn up with intercity trains?
[SPEAKER_05]: That's the most ridiculous spectacle I've ever seen in my entire life, a Mercedes with no bonnet, no front wings, no doors.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the hands of African Stig, though, it was flying.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is the latest in a long line of pedigree, lightened Mercedes-Benz sports cars.
[SPEAKER_05]: There's never been a Mercedes rally car.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, yours is flying up the hill, mate.
[SPEAKER_04]: Look at it go.
[SPEAKER_05]: You wait till you see the Lancia wheel dance through there.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, it's out of control.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's a big slide!
[SPEAKER_05]: One minute six.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'll just do my ancient... I hate you gloating.
[SPEAKER_05]: No, let him do it.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like winning a semi-final.
[SPEAKER_05]: Time now to put James in his place because the Lancia was on home turf with its rally pedigree.
[SPEAKER_05]: Stratos, 037.
[SPEAKER_05]: What?
[SPEAKER_08]: That's not dust, it's on fire!
[SPEAKER_08]: Can I turn it off?
[SPEAKER_08]: Look at it all!
[SPEAKER_03]: Stopwatch still running.
[SPEAKER_03]: 45 seconds.
[SPEAKER_05]: We'll replace the seal.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, when it's cooled down a bit, he'll be able to do the lap.
[SPEAKER_06]: He'll have difficulty, though.
[SPEAKER_06]: He's off.
[SPEAKER_06]: And maybe he started.
[SPEAKER_03]: Maybe... Start the stopwatch.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think he was in a hurry, so he decided not to take your car.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hey, Jeremy.
[SPEAKER_03]: What?
[SPEAKER_07]: You're right, though.
[SPEAKER_07]: Your engine.
[SPEAKER_07]: It's canted.
[SPEAKER_06]: Once again, the broken lance here was fixed.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then Jeremy arrived with some woe for all of us.
[SPEAKER_06]: What?
[SPEAKER_06]: Forget some of it.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Those are the fuel cans.
[SPEAKER_05]: The problem was that Richard's car and mine ran on leaded fuel, which was incredibly hard to find.
[SPEAKER_05]: And it was no use turning to the film crew for help.
[SPEAKER_05]: Diesel, diesel, diesel and two-stroke.
[SPEAKER_05]: Diesel... Guys, it's diesel and two-stroke.
[SPEAKER_06]: The town of Maun was about 60 miles away, and with little fuel, we'd have to go there as the crow flies.
[SPEAKER_06]: Now we really would see how they'd cope off-road.
[SPEAKER_06]: We've got to try and keep the distance down to save what fuel we've got.
[SPEAKER_05]: All we're looking for is a track indicating that other people have passed this way and they would be heading to a town.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's how broken my car is.
[SPEAKER_05]: I was doing that in park.
[SPEAKER_05]: These thorns are incredible.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, look at that.
[SPEAKER_05]: They've got like cocktail sticks growing out of them.
[SPEAKER_05]: Take cover.
[SPEAKER_06]: Once again, the 44-year-old Opel absolutely shone.
[SPEAKER_04]: Come on, little fella.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah!
[SPEAKER_06]: With our precious fuel burning away, we carved out the straightest path possible.
[SPEAKER_06]: Guys, you know what we're driving through?
[SPEAKER_06]: Plants.
[SPEAKER_06]: No, this is a weed.
[SPEAKER_06]: It grows locally and it's hallucinogenic.
[SPEAKER_06]: What did you say?
[SPEAKER_06]: If any car was going to get stuck, we would have put money on the Lance here, but no.
[SPEAKER_08]: All right, mate?
[SPEAKER_08]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_03]: All doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_03]: Clearly, I'd have to get myself out.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm going to make a rudimentary temporary road for my back wheel.
[SPEAKER_05]: Eventually, we found a smoother track.
[SPEAKER_04]: Whoa!
[SPEAKER_05]: And I did a detailed analysis of the Lancia's conditioning.
[SPEAKER_05]: Sit-rep.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's all broken.
[SPEAKER_06]: As darkness fell, we found the road to Man.
[SPEAKER_06]: But by this stage, even Oliver was suffering.
[SPEAKER_06]: I can't use my lights.
[SPEAKER_06]: Alternator's packed up all full of dirt and dust.
[SPEAKER_06]: If I put the lights on, I can have the lights, but not the engine, because it all dies.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I've actually got Jonathan, who brings all the cameras and does all that for us, in here with me, lighting me when I talk to you with the torch, which he then uses to light the road ahead when I'm not talking to you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Finally, we rolled into Man.
[SPEAKER_05]: Which year was it made?
1981.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's just driven all the way from Zimbabwe to here without going on a road.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like this?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Get out of the way of the pub.
[SPEAKER_05]: I shall move it for you.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you ask politely, I will move it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, that's his line.
[SPEAKER_06]: They are grown-ups, honestly.
[SPEAKER_06]: They do this a lot.
[SPEAKER_03]: We were now just over halfway, and amazingly, our cars were still running.
[SPEAKER_03]: All of them.
[SPEAKER_03]: The next day, in the centre of Maun, we got our next challenge.
[SPEAKER_03]: The Glittering Golden Envelope.
[SPEAKER_03]: You will drive your cars to Namibia through the Okavango Delta.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the really big wildlife place.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the Okavango, you will encounter many deadly animals, including lions, leopards, cheetahs, hyenas, wild dogs, hippos, black rhino and crocodile.
[SPEAKER_03]: Bird snakes, shield-nosed snakes, puff adders, boomslang, cape cobras, banded cobras, black mambas, black widows and thick-tailed scorpions.
[SPEAKER_05]: What about the honey badger?
[SPEAKER_05]: The what?
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the least scary-sounding animal in the world.
[SPEAKER_05]: A honey badger does not kill you to eat you.
[SPEAKER_05]: It tears off your testicles.
[SPEAKER_06]: It does not!
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is it called a honey badger?
[SPEAKER_06]: Because that's why it's made it angry.
[SPEAKER_06]: Why isn't it called the badger of death?
[SPEAKER_03]: In order to protect ourselves from the lions and the honey badgers, Jeremy and I would have to rebuild our cars.
[SPEAKER_03]: But because we'd left all the bits on the other side of the salt pans, we had to use whatever we could find.
[SPEAKER_03]: Did a lion eat this?
[SPEAKER_03]: Who do I see about the corrugated metal?
[SPEAKER_06]: I suppose I've had a practice, at least, with my lion drill.
[SPEAKER_08]: Oh, no, there's a lion coming.
[SPEAKER_06]: Ah, what shall I do?
[SPEAKER_06]: That.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oliver will protect me.
[SPEAKER_06]: Because I had nothing to do, I decided to irritate Jeremy.
[SPEAKER_05]: I want to go to that tarpaulin, then.
[SPEAKER_05]: Tarpaulin?
[SPEAKER_06]: Tarpaulin will defeat... Oh, no, it's well known, tarpaulin, for its almost military protective capabilities.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's why you often see people going into war zones draped in tarpaulin.
[SPEAKER_03]: Could you put a new door on a car?
[SPEAKER_03]: Come and have a look.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'll show you what I mean.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not sophisticated metalwork, this, but...
[SPEAKER_05]: I would like a tarpaulin roof for a Lancia Beta Coupe, 1981.
[SPEAKER_06]: We can.
[SPEAKER_06]: We can make anything here.
[SPEAKER_06]: Do you have any lion-proof tarpaulin?
[SPEAKER_06]: So it's got to be, like, this thick.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: One and a half metres by, say, one and a half metres.
[SPEAKER_06]: If you think of a lion door, it'd be about that big.
[SPEAKER_06]: Could you ignore him and make me that?
[SPEAKER_05]: Because Mercedes were very popular in Africa, James soon found a spare door and boot lid for his car.
[SPEAKER_05]: And while he was looking for more bits, I hatched a plan.
[SPEAKER_05]: Look what I've got.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's a cow's head.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Now, this will attract flies, which will make his life unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: It will also attract lions, tigers... He effectively becomes a burger van, a driving van.
[SPEAKER_06]: And to make sure the lions didn't miss... Oh, yeah, that's a whopper.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's a whole lion there.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, yeah, under the seat.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, the smell will really... That'll be beautiful.
[SPEAKER_06]: We also attached a cowbell to the underside of his car.
[SPEAKER_06]: But while we were doing this, he was making merry with the paint.
[SPEAKER_06]: That afternoon, we left Man and headed north to the Okavango Delta.
[SPEAKER_05]: Right, my car now has been readied.
[SPEAKER_05]: As you can see, I have a wooden door here.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a gull-wing, so I can get in and out, obviously.
[SPEAKER_03]: God, this is like being in an allotment shed... on a very windy day.
[SPEAKER_05]: On the left, I have all the cans that were in the car for the last few days have been arranged, and Fiesta Resistance.
[SPEAKER_05]: Badgers, go away.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mad Jeremy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Police car.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can anybody else smell burning or is it my car?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it like a barbecue smell?
[SPEAKER_03]: As we neared the Okavango, the roads became rougher and rougher.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is where the Big Ben comes into its own, really, because it's got good ground clearance, nothing... Bloody hell.
[SPEAKER_05]: This is enough to shake the skulls from your bonnet, and nobody in the whole of human history has ever said that before.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, just to summarise, viewers... As we went through the gates and into the game reserve, the road changed again, for the worse.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is new.
[SPEAKER_03]: Very soft sand.
[SPEAKER_03]: To stop our cars bogging down, we had to drive as fast as possible.
[SPEAKER_03]: We had ourselves another rally stage.
[SPEAKER_03]: Amazingly, even Jeremy had his work cut out keeping up with the Opel.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hammond's car just looks so composed.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm developing this irrational hatred of him and it.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is such a good game.
[SPEAKER_05]: Eventually, he was slowed down by a bridge over the river Kwai.
[SPEAKER_05]: The rally stage had taken its toll on one of the cars.
[SPEAKER_05]: Take a guess which one.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm in a car, which is even probably here, has got a throttle that's jammed wide open and I can't hold it on the brakes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hammond, move!
[SPEAKER_04]: You're going to have to go faster than I hit you.
[SPEAKER_04]: What?
[SPEAKER_08]: Oh, God!
[SPEAKER_08]: Thanks!
[SPEAKER_08]: Well, help yourself to my brakes, why not?
[SPEAKER_08]: I've lost a skull.
[SPEAKER_03]: Monkeys.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm sorry, I can't... I just hit the throttle.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's tick over.
[SPEAKER_05]: Look, my leg's not on it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Having blotched my throttle, we headed deeper into the Okavango.
[SPEAKER_05]: Front, 12 o'clock.
[SPEAKER_05]: One o'clock.
[SPEAKER_05]: This is where wildlife cameramen come to make a name for themselves with David Attenborough.
[SPEAKER_05]: But unfortunately, our film crew are best, really, with cars.
[SPEAKER_02]: A giraffe on the right.
[SPEAKER_02]: There.
[SPEAKER_02]: The big thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: Little fluffy clouds.
[SPEAKER_05]: We have a programme called The Back End of an Animal.
[SPEAKER_05]: Meet the boys to hire.
[SPEAKER_05]: This week on Too Late to Look.
[SPEAKER_06]: A moon on the left with animals with a baby on its back.
[SPEAKER_05]: To give our crew a chance, we stopped and discovered that we weren't much good at animals either.
[SPEAKER_05]: Wow, look!
[SPEAKER_05]: Look!
[SPEAKER_03]: A hippo's head.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, it is!
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it's probably a whole hippo.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just the rest of him is under the water.
[SPEAKER_06]: What does a hippo do just before it's about to attack?
[SPEAKER_05]: Opens its mouth.
[SPEAKER_05]: It can open its jaw.
[SPEAKER_05]: There's a thing it can do.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, look!
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, look at that!
[SPEAKER_05]: They stop for a drink.
[SPEAKER_05]: using their noses to shovel water into their mouths.
[SPEAKER_06]: Jeremy, that's a rubbish commentary.
[SPEAKER_03]: James took over.
[SPEAKER_03]: That one's lifting its paw up a bit like a dog does.
[SPEAKER_03]: Paw.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hoof.
[SPEAKER_03]: Foot.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whatever you call it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hoof.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is it on an elephant?
[SPEAKER_05]: It's amazing.
[SPEAKER_05]: There's a man over there with the best comb-over I have ever seen in my life.
[SPEAKER_05]: That is...
[SPEAKER_03]: He's got four partings as a result of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's see.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why don't... You're bald.
[SPEAKER_07]: Live with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oops, he caught me looking.
[SPEAKER_07]: I was looking through the... Sorry.
[SPEAKER_05]: I was looking at the elephants, really.
[SPEAKER_05]: Look at that sun now, boys.
[SPEAKER_05]: Elephants, rally special stage, best comb-over I've ever seen.
[SPEAKER_05]: Everything's here.
[SPEAKER_06]: We camped by the river, and while James serviced his car, I hatched a plan.
[SPEAKER_07]: Jeremy.
[SPEAKER_06]: Jeremy.
Quick, come here.
Come here.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's the cow's head.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, well, it wasn't working in the boat.
I've had a better idea.
What?
[SPEAKER_06]: Ten.
[SPEAKER_06]: His ten?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Love your thinking.
What's that?
It was a hippo.
[SPEAKER_09]: What?
[SPEAKER_09]: Plugs.
[SPEAKER_09]: That sounded very close.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, my God, look at that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hippos spend all day in water and then they come out at night because... I can't remember why.
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's useful.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, brilliant.
[SPEAKER_05]: Look, do you want to go out there with the hippopotamus?
[SPEAKER_06]: Or do you want to stay in here where the horse is sat?
[SPEAKER_06]: That's not a question that's ever been asked.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's not a horse, either.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's a cow.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hang on.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's my bag in James's tent.
[SPEAKER_08]: This is my tent!
[SPEAKER_08]: Oh, man, get it out!
[SPEAKER_05]: Our starting point at the Zimbabwe border felt like it was in another time zone.
[SPEAKER_05]: But still, there were many miles of delta to cover, and our cars were in a really bad way.
[SPEAKER_05]: The bush mechanic we have on the team took two cubic feet of sand out of my carburettor last night and asked if I wouldn't mind driving a bit more slowly today.
[SPEAKER_05]: James, he's coming!
[SPEAKER_05]: Our ordinary second-hand road cars were getting more and more out of their depth.
[SPEAKER_05]: This is proper off-roading now.
[SPEAKER_05]: Men in camouflage trousers in Wales, who like murdering people at weekends, would say this was tough going.
[SPEAKER_08]: It was a whole... Oh!
[SPEAKER_06]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_06]: It's like iron.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think I've bent the steering back a bit.
[SPEAKER_04]: Wow!
[SPEAKER_03]: Wow, there is an elephant right there.
[SPEAKER_05]: A door there.
[SPEAKER_05]: That would stop an elephant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Soon our route was blocked by a river and what you're supposed to do is wade in to check the depth.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jeremy made us drive on until he got bored.
[SPEAKER_03]: Here, now.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: I agree with him, for once, actually, because that reedy stuff must mean it's shallow.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's shallow where the reeds are, you fool.
[SPEAKER_05]: We'll just drive over to where the reeds are, then.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes, but you've got to drive through the water to get there.
[SPEAKER_05]: We can't keep going.
[SPEAKER_05]: We've done 30 miles.
[SPEAKER_06]: No, I'm frustrated, but you can't just drive into a river because you're bored.
[SPEAKER_06]: I do a fair bit of off-roading, and I know enough that that's not the place to go across.
[SPEAKER_06]: You're wrong.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm going through here.
[SPEAKER_05]: Are you going to carry on?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, well, I will carry on if you're going to go through there.
[SPEAKER_05]: Keep your radio on.
[SPEAKER_06]: All right.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm going.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm not doing a four-by-four.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, so edging.
[SPEAKER_05]: Fan belts off.
[SPEAKER_05]: Fan belts off is a good idea.
[SPEAKER_05]: Cos it'll splash water into the distributors.
[SPEAKER_05]: James went first and I said I'd watch for crocodiles.
[SPEAKER_05]: Ooh, I say there's a ground hornbill over there.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's getting deeper.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ooh, hang on a minute.
[SPEAKER_03]: Permission to say cock.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's coming in!
[SPEAKER_03]: Thunderbird one to the rescue.
[SPEAKER_04]: Come on, I'm sinking by the bows.
[SPEAKER_04]: Coming.
[SPEAKER_04]: No!
[SPEAKER_04]: I can't help you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Come on.
[SPEAKER_04]: James, I'm in a low, slow sports car.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm going down.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's good.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes!
[SPEAKER_04]: I've got water coming into my car.
[SPEAKER_04]: I've got a wet bottom!
[SPEAKER_04]: We're through!
[SPEAKER_05]: Both our cars were flooded, but our guides weren't bothered at all.
[SPEAKER_05]: People of Surrey, if this happens to you, you get water in the footwell and you need to drain it out, you're going to need a hole.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, the people of Botswana have a tip for you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Meanwhile, using patience, I'd found a proper crossing point.
[SPEAKER_06]: There is a technique to fording rivers, even on a proper ford like this.
[SPEAKER_06]: You've got to keep enough speed up so you push a bow wave like that and you use whatever power you've got in the engine.
[SPEAKER_06]: Come on.
[SPEAKER_06]: Come on, come on.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, my... No!
[SPEAKER_08]: Oh, God!
[SPEAKER_08]: He's stalled!
[SPEAKER_08]: He's going down!
[SPEAKER_08]: I can't open the door!
[SPEAKER_08]: Oh, God!
[SPEAKER_08]: Please!
[SPEAKER_08]: Come out!
[SPEAKER_08]: Come on!
[SPEAKER_08]: Float!
[SPEAKER_08]: Oliver!
[SPEAKER_05]: Hammond, how's it going?
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, I got a bit of water in him.
[SPEAKER_05]: We did as well, but it doesn't matter because we used some rifles.
[SPEAKER_05]: We shot the cars and the water's all drained out.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's brilliant.
[SPEAKER_06]: Good.
[SPEAKER_06]: I might need the rifle.
[SPEAKER_06]: As a local tourist truck pulled me out, the laughing hyenas arrived.
[SPEAKER_06]: May gave his diagnosis.
[SPEAKER_03]: Starting from the top, the battery's probably pretty knackered, and then the carburettor will be flooded, in a literal sense.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then working down the distributor cap, that'll be full of water.
[SPEAKER_03]: The engine itself, I mean, if a bit of water went into the cylinders, you might have compressed it and broken something.
[SPEAKER_03]: The oil will be ruined.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know all this.
[SPEAKER_06]: I can fix him.
[SPEAKER_05]: You are going to try and mend this?
[SPEAKER_06]: If you'd leave me to it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So we did.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, that's harsh.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is quite harsh, but go on.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, I like this one.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's sad, so sad.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a sad, sad situation.
[SPEAKER_05]: Unfortunately, you can only give a man so much sympathy.
[SPEAKER_05]: So James and I went ahead to make camp.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hammond knew that in the morning, if his beloved Oliver wasn't fixed, he'd have to leave him behind.
[SPEAKER_05]: So he got our bush mechanic to bring the generator down... ..and worked on through the night.
[SPEAKER_05]: Morning came and still no Hammond.
[SPEAKER_05]: What happened today?
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, I'm feeling quite like an explorer.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is that Hammond?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it a beetle more to the point?
No way.
[SPEAKER_05]: No way.
[SPEAKER_08]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, he's back.
[SPEAKER_06]: And here's the best thing.
[SPEAKER_06]: Do you remember the horn, which was rubbish?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's excellent.
[SPEAKER_05]: Is that technically possible?
[SPEAKER_05]: Probably not.
[SPEAKER_05]: For 47 years, I've never been speechless.
[SPEAKER_05]: With all the cars defying all the odds, we began our final push to the border.
[SPEAKER_03]: My car is working perfectly, as usual.
[SPEAKER_06]: I've got no brakes.
[SPEAKER_06]: The pedal goes straight to the floor and I have to declutch to stop, so I just tread on my own foot.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I'm using the handbrake.
[SPEAKER_06]: Ha!
[SPEAKER_05]: The Lancia could beat that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Every time I brake, it spears off to the right and I'm unable to steer left to correct that.
[SPEAKER_05]: This has now gone from being a nuisance to being downright dangerous.
[SPEAKER_03]: We soon reached the end of the Okavango, so we pulled over to remove the animal protection.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, guess what?
[SPEAKER_03]: The Lancia simply would not get going again.
[SPEAKER_03]: It now won't start, because the starter's only chosen this moment to pack up, but when it was running, it wouldn't move off in any of the gears.
[SPEAKER_05]: It was just that last 60k.
[SPEAKER_05]: It had that feel of a car that was dying.
[SPEAKER_05]: Richard actually sympathised, because he'd been there.
[SPEAKER_05]: As for James... A vehicle.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm not going to do it, but I'll push it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is this a good time to acknowledge that mine is the only one that has worked consistently?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is worrying.
[SPEAKER_03]: I need to be home by Saturday.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've been invited to a beetle drive.
[SPEAKER_05]: The entire crew was working on the stricken beater until we were rewarded with the most glorious sound in the world.
[SPEAKER_05]: Life.
[SPEAKER_05]: I got a whole hundred yards.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm not stuck.
[SPEAKER_04]: The idle speed's not good.
[SPEAKER_04]: Bye, everybody.
[SPEAKER_04]: I can't stop.
[SPEAKER_04]: Please.
[SPEAKER_06]: Soon, we hit the tarmac and we started to taste the hope.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just 20 miles.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've crossed Botswana.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I'm stuck in second, but second will do.
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, I might have to keep going to the other side of the whole continent, but, you know... Come on, ten miles, please!
[SPEAKER_06]: Then something really surprising happened.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, no, not now.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because the Lancia had been such a problem child, everyone was fed up with it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Only two of the crew stayed behind to help.
[SPEAKER_05]: The carburettor's gone.
[SPEAKER_05]: Even if we can get that fixed, the starter motor is gone.
[SPEAKER_05]: We've put it into gear, it goes into third and then that just stalls the engine and then you're back to square one again.
[SPEAKER_05]: The Bordo was just five miles away.
[SPEAKER_03]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is an object lesson for the owners of old cars everywhere.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can drive them round the world.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, it's really relaxing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Come on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Order!
[SPEAKER_03]: 1,596 kilometres.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's nearest I'm at 1,000 miles.
[SPEAKER_03]: I've still got half a car left and very bad hair.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't believe that.
[SPEAKER_08]: Sorry, I've got no brakes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_06]: We've done it!
[SPEAKER_06]: All we had to do now was wait.
[SPEAKER_06]: Wait to see which car Jeremy arrived in.
[SPEAKER_06]: Is that an engine?
[SPEAKER_03]: That's a car.
[SPEAKER_03]: A mistakeable clatter of an air-cooled engine.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's going to be the Beetle.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it was.
[SPEAKER_05]: But I wasn't driving it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, I'm almost pleased.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes!
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, that's excellent.
[SPEAKER_04]: Watch it!
[SPEAKER_04]: Brakes don't work!
[SPEAKER_03]: Sorry, there's no brakes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Congratulations.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's astonishing.
[SPEAKER_05]: I think, realistically, we have to say the Lancia's won it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Why?
[SPEAKER_06]: By what possible measure?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you... It's the most surprising.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the worst.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, well, you don't buy a second-hand car to be surprised that it still works.
[SPEAKER_03]: It had to be rebuilt once a day.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but you're right, it's rubbish.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mercedes is the best car.
[SPEAKER_03]: What?
[SPEAKER_03]: What have I had to do?
[SPEAKER_03]: I've had to change... Take the entire body off.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a showroom model, James.
[SPEAKER_03]: All right, I admit that it's not entirely original, but in mechanical terms, it was perfect.
[SPEAKER_03]: You cannot break it.
[SPEAKER_05]: I think, honestly, we have to be magnanimous here, because only one of the cars has actually made it unmodified.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that brings us on to a Top Gear top tip.
[SPEAKER_05]: If, people of Surrey, you want to replace your BMW X5 with something that's brilliant off-road... Simple.
[SPEAKER_05]: Simple, inexpensive... Easy to maintain, surprisingly comfortable.
[SPEAKER_05]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then you've got to get yourself a Volkswagen Beetle.
What?
[SPEAKER_05]: It's true.
[SPEAKER_05]: No, he's right.
[SPEAKER_04]: He's right.
[SPEAKER_04]: You've replaced all the electrics in that car.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tomorrow night at 8.50, it's more from the Top Gear lads with a Bolivia special as Jeremy, James and Richard are driving all the way to the coast of Chile from the heart of the jungle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's hope they bring enough glove compartment snacks.
[SPEAKER_00]: And up next, it's Sherlock on three.