[SPEAKER_01]: He's protecting the important bits.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keen to get going, the three of us fired up our engines.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, when I say three.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's absolutely dead.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nothing is functioning.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is no electrical... You two are not being helpful.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: What a stupid thing to say.
[SPEAKER_03]: Interior light, headlight?
[SPEAKER_03]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't know how to mend the ignition circuit on a 1981 Lancia Beetle?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's... It was a long shot.
[SPEAKER_01]: Annoyingly, a couple of the locals did know what to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we drove to African Stig's rally stage, which was in a dried-up riverbed a few miles away.
[SPEAKER_01]: With packed spectator stands, Oliver went first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Three, two...
[SPEAKER_03]: One.
[SPEAKER_03]: Go!
[SPEAKER_01]: Three miles an hour.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, when it was new, it had 40 horsepower.
[SPEAKER_03]: If it's lost one a year, it's at minus four.
[SPEAKER_03]: He's going round the first corner.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_03]: That was a power slide.
[SPEAKER_03]: Look at that.
[SPEAKER_03]: It does look... Ridiculous is the word you're looking for.
[SPEAKER_03]: As the cadets struggle to get up the hill, the spectators left.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is eminent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Come on, joggle it, Stig's cousin.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's enjoying that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And one minute, 12 seconds.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think that's a good benchmark for you to try and beat.
[SPEAKER_02]: Next up was the Panzer Tank.
[SPEAKER_02]: Most powerful, longest, best tyres... Longest?
[SPEAKER_03]: Longest is good for rallying, is it?
[SPEAKER_03]: It is on this, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So why doesn't... On loose surface rallies, don't they turn up with intercity trains?
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the most ridiculous spectacle I've ever seen in my entire life, a Mercedes with no bonnet, no front wings, no doors.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the hands of African Stig, though, it was flying.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is the latest in a long line of pedigree lightened Mercedes-Benz sports cars.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's never been a Mercedes rally car.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, yours is flying up the hill, mate.
[SPEAKER_03]: Look at it go.
[SPEAKER_03]: You wait till you see the Lancia wheel dance through there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, it's out of control.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's a big slide!
[SPEAKER_03]: One minute six.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'll just do my ancient... I hate you gloating.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, let him do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like winning a semi-final.
[SPEAKER_03]: Time now to put James in his place because the Lancia was on home turf with its rally pedigree.
[SPEAKER_03]: Stratos, 037.
[SPEAKER_03]: What?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not dust, it's on fire!
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I turn it off?
[SPEAKER_01]: Look at it all!
[SPEAKER_02]: Stopwatch still running.
[SPEAKER_02]: 45 seconds.
[SPEAKER_03]: We'll replace the seal.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, when it's cooled down a bit, he'll be able to do the lap.
[SPEAKER_00]: He'll have difficulty, though.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's off.
[SPEAKER_00]: And maybe he started.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe... Start the stopwatch.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think he was in a hurry, so he decided not to take your car.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hey, Jeremy.
[SPEAKER_02]: What?
[SPEAKER_00]: You're right, though.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your engine.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's canted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once again, the broken lance here was fixed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then Jeremy arrived with some woe for all of us.
[SPEAKER_01]: What?
[SPEAKER_01]: Forget some of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are the fuel cans.
[SPEAKER_03]: The problem was that Richard's car and mine ran on leaded fuel, which was incredibly hard to find.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it was no use turning to the film crew for help.
[SPEAKER_03]: Diesel, diesel, diesel and two-stroke.
[SPEAKER_03]: Diesel... Guys, it's diesel and two-stroke.
[SPEAKER_01]: The town of Maun was about 60 miles away, and with little fuel, we'd have to go there as the crow flies.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now we really would see how they'd cope off-road.
[SPEAKER_01]: We've got to try and keep the distance down to save what fuel we've got.
[SPEAKER_03]: All we're looking for is a track indicating that other people have passed this way and they would be heading to a town.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how broken my car is.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was doing that in park.
[SPEAKER_03]: These thorns are incredible.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, look at that.
[SPEAKER_03]: They've got like cocktail sticks growing out of them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Take cover.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once again, the 44-year-old Opel absolutely shone.
[SPEAKER_03]: Come on, little fella.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah!
[SPEAKER_01]: With our precious fuel burning away, we carved out the straightest path possible.