[SPEAKER_00]: built in Russia, where it became the Moskvitch, which was rubbish.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, of course, indirectly, the Vauxhall Astra.
[SPEAKER_00]: Quite a lot of reasonably average cars owe themselves to this.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know if you know, but Africa is really quite large, and when you're out in a very remote part, you need a car like this, that can be mended with a brick and a piece of string.
[SPEAKER_02]: What you have to remember is that three of the most rugged and successful rally cars ever made were Lancia's.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Stratos, the 037 and the Delta Integrale.
[SPEAKER_02]: Lancia know how to make a rally car.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unfortunately, on the day my beauté coupé was made, they obviously forgot everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: The gearbox is broken, the steering's broken, the window's broken.
[SPEAKER_02]: In fact, we all had problems.
[SPEAKER_03]: Everything works except this knob, which controls the blood.
[SPEAKER_03]: I've got to have the windows open because there's quite a strong smell of petrol.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that mirror over there, which is actually slightly stuck.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hazard warning lights, the clock, the fan, the handbrake, all of the dials.
[SPEAKER_00]: The brakes are terrible because they only work on that wheel.
[SPEAKER_00]: They work very well on that wheel, but only on that wheel.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that instrument's a bit wobbly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Apart from that, everything that's actually important to the car works perfectly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Apart from the handbrake, which I can pull like this as we go along.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nevertheless, because we were on tarmac roads, we decided to give our cars a shakedown.
[SPEAKER_02]: Building up speed now.
[SPEAKER_02]: When it was made, this car had 116 horsepower.
[SPEAKER_02]: Top speed, 115 miles an hour.
[SPEAKER_02]: Here we go.
[SPEAKER_02]: Going 100 kilometres an hour more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, I'm going to overtake the truck.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here I go.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's pulled out of its slipstream.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's really coming up.
105.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still truck.
[SPEAKER_03]: 3,000 revs, 3,500.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pulls cleanly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hang on a minute.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's got no fifth gear.
[SPEAKER_03]: Somebody's put the knob from a five-gear model on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is just the happiest car in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: As we call it, Oliver.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not that we'd ever name a car on top of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wish I hadn't said that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's now five past ten in the morning and it's starting to get quite hot.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've got an idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's better.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't know what that is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The horn!
[SPEAKER_00]: Oliver, you've got a cold!
[SPEAKER_00]: Listen!
[SPEAKER_00]: We were having fun, but then we discovered we were travelling with Bill Oddie.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why have you got a pen?
[SPEAKER_02]: You tick them off when you've seen them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hornbill, southern yellowbill.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take a look at your car.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's massive!
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't knock Oliver.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't knock my car.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a fine... He's a fine... What did you call it, then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oliver's a friend of mine and I thought you were talking about him.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's given it a name.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's given his car a name.
[SPEAKER_02]: So far, the journey had been a doddle.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then the tarmac just sort of stopped.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, this is bad.
[SPEAKER_03]: I can see from here just how hard the suspension on Jeremy's Lance is having to work.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just a blur.
[SPEAKER_00]: Come on, Oliver, please!
[SPEAKER_03]: The later you book a lift in the Mercedes, the more expensive it gets.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a bit like an airline.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, God!
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh!
[SPEAKER_03]: Engine isn't working, it's cut out.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, dear.
[SPEAKER_03]: He's done literally one kilometre of this.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know what's wrong with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: The bonnet won't open.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it's the bonnet catch.
[SPEAKER_02]: Shut up!
[SPEAKER_02]: Hammond was tetchy because he knew the price of failure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Anyone whose car broke down would have to complete the journey in a beetle.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is collectively our least favourite car in the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is the punishment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Please!
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, hang on, hang on.
Oh!
[SPEAKER_02]: Come on, Oliver!
[SPEAKER_02]: What did you say?
[SPEAKER_00]: I said, I love you!
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, my God.
[SPEAKER_00]: What now?
[SPEAKER_02]: My car's on fire, but in a very specific place.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wow, look at that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a magnifying glass.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a laser beam coming through it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, his piece of cardboard's gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it sets itself on fire?
[SPEAKER_02]: If you don't have a piece of cardboard.