[SPEAKER_02]: Back up to strength, we pressed on, apart from Jeremy being Bill Oddie occasionally.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is where flamingos breed out here.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's breeding, is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a fossil.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a fossil.
[SPEAKER_00]: It only died about two years ago.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was talking about you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an ex-flamingo.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hey, no, look.
[SPEAKER_00]: What now?
[SPEAKER_00]: I know what created this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ostrich.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes!
[SPEAKER_00]: Its legs are miles apart.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly how it was walking.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, David Attenborough's about to retire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I just say... What?
[SPEAKER_00]: You look like a gay cowboy and you look like a gay terrorist.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you look like a terrorist with a broken windscreen wiper and your face is ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ern Hammond started to pick on my car.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why haven't you turned it on?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's gathering electricity.
[SPEAKER_02]: So if you turn it off, the battery's not going to start it again.
[SPEAKER_02]: Turn it off and start it then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, go on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Turn it off and start it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's have some beautiful silence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you ready?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Behold... Why did you turn it off, you idiot?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he said it would... Good luck, mate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Somebody will give you a dub stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Goodbye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Annoyingly, Clarkson got the lancet going again.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then we came across some big birds.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wow!
And then we saw even more wildlife.
There's a cow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Two cows, three cows.
Yes!
We've done it!
[SPEAKER_00]: We had crossed the Mercati caddy.
[SPEAKER_02]: Trees!
[SPEAKER_02]: Life!
[SPEAKER_02]: Mate, did you ever think that you'd do that?
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm genuinely proud of him.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: Really, I'm startled that this... that isn't a car anymore, whatever it is, has done it.
[SPEAKER_00]: with its low-profile tyres and its low suspension that's broken.
[SPEAKER_01]: Personally, I'm absolutely delighted because I think the Macaddy Caddy is one of the most unpleasant places I've ever been.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a big bowl of dust.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hello, mate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Widow Twankey may have been glad to see the back of the salt pans, but despite this, they gave us a startling parting gift.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wow, that is amazing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the moon.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's the moon.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of the dust from the pans, you get... A moonrise in orange.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've got goosebumps.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know a Philip Larkin poem about the moon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you like to hear it?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a new day dawned, our cars looked like wrecks.
[SPEAKER_00]: But their ordeal was far from over.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, we had crossed the salt pans, but we were still only a third of the way across Botswana.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now we were about to enter the Kalahari.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kalahari.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everyone who comes to the Kalahari takes away a different memory of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Savagery, the simplicity, the vast heat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Me, I think bumpiness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was as rough as hell, so we were glad when news came through that we were to stop at the next village.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, they recognise a truly classy car.
[SPEAKER_00]: What could they possibly have in mind for us here?
[SPEAKER_00]: It was another challenge.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hello.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your cars have travelled far and suffered much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, they have.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we will now discover how much performance they've lost in a competition against the clock on a rally special stage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mine can't have lost any performance.
[SPEAKER_00]: It never added any.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I'm not going to ruin my Mercedes just for a few points.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're right, you're not, because you're not driving it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, who is?
[SPEAKER_00]: Some say he's seen the Lion King 1,780 times, and that his second best friend is a Cape buffalo.
[SPEAKER_00]: All we know is he's not the Stig, but he is the Stig's African cousin.