[SPEAKER_03]: Using patience, I'd found a proper crossing point.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is a technique to fording rivers, even on a proper ford like this.
[SPEAKER_03]: You've got to keep enough speed up so you push a bow wave like that and you use whatever power you've got in the engine.
[SPEAKER_03]: Come on, come on, come on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, my... No!
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, God!
[SPEAKER_02]: He's stalled!
[SPEAKER_02]: He's going down!
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't open the door!
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, God!
[SPEAKER_02]: Please!
[SPEAKER_02]: Come out!
[SPEAKER_02]: Come on!
[SPEAKER_02]: Float!
[SPEAKER_02]: Oliver!
[SPEAKER_01]: Hammond, how's it going?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, I got a bit of water in him.
[SPEAKER_01]: We did as well, but it doesn't matter because we used some rifles.
[SPEAKER_01]: We shot the cars and the water's all drained out.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's brilliant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Good.
[SPEAKER_03]: I might need the rifle.
[SPEAKER_03]: As a local tourist truck pulled me out, the laughing hyenas arrived.
[SPEAKER_03]: May gave his diagnosis.
[SPEAKER_00]: Starting from the top, the battery's probably pretty knackered, and then the carburettor will be flooded, in a literal sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then working down the distributor cap, that'll be full of water.
[SPEAKER_00]: The engine itself, I mean, if a bit of water went into the cylinders, you might have compressed it and broken something.
[SPEAKER_00]: The oil will be ruined.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know all this.
[SPEAKER_03]: I can fix him.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are going to try and mend this?
[SPEAKER_03]: If you'd leave me to it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we did.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, that's harsh.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is quite harsh, but go on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I like this one.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's sad, so sad.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a sad, sad situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unfortunately, you can only give a man so much sympathy.
[SPEAKER_01]: So James and I went ahead to make camp.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hammond knew that in the morning, if his beloved Oliver wasn't fixed, he'd have to leave him behind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So he got our bush mechanic to bring the generator down... ..and worked on through the night.
[SPEAKER_01]: Morning came and still no Hammond.
[SPEAKER_01]: What happened today?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I'm feeling quite like an explorer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that Hammond?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it a beetle more to the point?
No way.
[SPEAKER_01]: No way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, he's back.
[SPEAKER_03]: And here's the best thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you remember the horn, which was rubbish?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's excellent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that technically possible?
[SPEAKER_01]: Probably not.
[SPEAKER_01]: For 47 years, I've never been speechless.
[SPEAKER_01]: With all the cars defying all the odds, we began our final push to the border.
[SPEAKER_00]: My car is working perfectly, as usual.
[SPEAKER_03]: I've got no brakes.
[SPEAKER_03]: The pedal goes straight to the floor and I have to declutch to stop, so I just tread on my own foot.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I'm using the handbrake.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ha!
[SPEAKER_01]: The Lancia could beat that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every time I brake, it spears off to the right and I'm unable to steer left to correct that.
[SPEAKER_01]: This has now gone from being a nuisance to being downright dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: We soon reached the end of the Okavango, so we pulled over to remove the animal protection.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, guess what?
[SPEAKER_00]: The Lancia simply would not get going again.
[SPEAKER_00]: It now won't start, because the starter's only chosen this moment to pack up, but when it was running, it wouldn't move off in any of the gears.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was just that last 60k.
[SPEAKER_01]: It had that feel of a car that was dying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Richard actually sympathised, because he'd been there.
[SPEAKER_01]: As for James... A vehicle.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not going to give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll push it.