[SPEAKER_02]: Is this a good time to acknowledge that mine is the only one that has worked consistently?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is worrying.
[SPEAKER_02]: I need to be home by Saturday.
[SPEAKER_03]: I've been invited to a beetle drive.
[SPEAKER_03]: The entire crew was working on the stricken beater until we were rewarded with the most glorious sound in the world.
Life.
[SPEAKER_03]: It lives!
It lives!
[SPEAKER_03]: I got a whole hundred yards.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not stuck.
[SPEAKER_03]: The idle speed's not good.
[SPEAKER_03]: Bye, everybody.
[SPEAKER_03]: I can't stop.
[SPEAKER_03]: Please.
[SPEAKER_04]: Soon, we hit the tarmac and we started to taste the hope.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just 20 miles.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You've crossed Botswana.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, I'm stuck in second, but second will do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, mine would keep going to the other side of the whole continent, but, you know... Come on, ten miles, please!
[SPEAKER_04]: Then something really surprising happened.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, no, not now.
Please!
[SPEAKER_03]: Because the Lancia had been such a problem child, everyone was fed up with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Only two of the crew stayed behind to help.
[SPEAKER_03]: Carburettors gone.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if we can get that fixed, the starter motor is gone.
[SPEAKER_03]: We put it into gear, it goes into third, and then that just stalls the engine and then you're back to square one again.
[SPEAKER_03]: The Bordo was just five miles away.
[SPEAKER_01]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is an object lesson for the owners of old cars everywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can drive them round the world.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, it's really relaxing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Come on.
[SPEAKER_04]: Bordo!
[SPEAKER_01]: 1,596 kilometres.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's near as damn it a thousand miles.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've still got half a car left and very bad hair.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't believe that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sorry, I've got no brakes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_04]: We've done it.
[SPEAKER_04]: All we had to do now was wait, wait to see which car Jeremy arrived in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that an engine?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a car.
[SPEAKER_02]: A mistakeable clatter of an air-cooled engine.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's going to be the Beetle.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it was.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I wasn't driving it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, I'm almost pleased.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes!
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, that's excellent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry, there's no brakes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Congratulations.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's astonishing.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think, realistically, we have to say the Lancia's won it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why?
[SPEAKER_04]: By what possible measure?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, you... It's the most surprising.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the worst.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, well, you don't buy a second-hand car to be surprised that it still works.
[SPEAKER_02]: It had to be rebuilt once a day.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but you're right, it's rubbish.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mercedes is the best car.
[SPEAKER_02]: What?
[SPEAKER_02]: What have I had to do?
[SPEAKER_02]: I've had to change... Take the entire body off.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a showroom model, James.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right, I admit that it's not entirely original, but in mechanical terms, it was perfect.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot break it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think, honestly, we have to be magnanimous here, because only one of the cars has actually made it unmodified.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that brings us on to a Top Gear top tip.
[SPEAKER_03]: If, people of Surrey, you want to replace your BMW X5 with something that's brilliant off-road... Simple.
[SPEAKER_03]: Simple, inexpensive... Easy to maintain, surprisingly comfortable.
[SPEAKER_03]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then you've got to get yourself a Volkswagen Beetle.
What?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's true.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, he's right.
[SPEAKER_03]: He's right.
[SPEAKER_03]: You've replaced all the electrics in that car.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tomorrow night at 8.50, it's more from the Top Gear lads with a Bolivia special as Jeremy, James and Richard are driving all the way to the coast of Chile from the heart of the jungle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's hope they bring enough glove compartment snacks.
[SPEAKER_00]: And up next, it's Sherlock on three.