[SPEAKER_00]: I'm digging in as I'm driving along.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think a little bit more has to come out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Still, as you can see from the tyres' grooves, I was doing better than the Merc.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm looking at James's rear wheel and he's digging in a long way.
[SPEAKER_00]: I tried to help him along.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's really helpful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, he's always the beetle, James.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's waiting for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are you going to do?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's sinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Honestly, we've done... How far is that, a mile?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: My Lancia waded in again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just a nudge.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a crash.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unfortunately, because it was an automatic, it was useless.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we told Richard to try.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he didn't want to hurt Oliver.
[SPEAKER_00]: This was hopeless, so we had to rope in the camera crew.
[SPEAKER_00]: Three, two, one... Because the ooze was so bad, we had to get even more drastic with the weight-shedding.
[SPEAKER_00]: We toiled away for hours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, two of us did.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, finally, we were ready.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, this is light.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lancia, Beta, Coupe, Superleggera.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not a modification.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is excellent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why don't all cars have no doors?
[SPEAKER_00]: When I come to power, I'm going to make it a rule, because this is just better.
[SPEAKER_00]: However, the Mercati Caddy was not going to let us off that lightly, and soon even our super lightweight cars started to struggle again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Come on, just... Oh.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, this isn't good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only the Opel remained trouble-free, which was bad news for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes!
[SPEAKER_00]: Come on, man.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll go forward, Sam, and then we'll do it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hang on.
[SPEAKER_00]: How far is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Another five or six yards and we might be bobbing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is just horrible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep going, keep going, keep going.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep going.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes!
Yes!
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: James, don't go there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll get stuck.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's close.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, for goodness' sake.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have everybody, we'll push it off.
[SPEAKER_00]: We need 100 men or more.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is hopeless.
[SPEAKER_00]: People of Surrey, you need four-wheel drive for this bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: The gunk was so sticky, it had completely jammed the Lancia's rear wheels.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't describe it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just think it's just mud.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you know what it is?
[SPEAKER_00]: Fish.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just rotted, prehistoric fish.
[SPEAKER_00]: One, two, three.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mercifully, the ground eventually hardened and we made good progress.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then suddenly, the horizon was no longer flat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, this is interesting, because we're now coming between what look like islands.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I suppose they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: This was a lake, so they would have been islands.
[SPEAKER_00]: Amazing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely amazing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where are we?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's called Kubu Island.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're about...
[SPEAKER_00]: A third of the way across.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you've been stuck about a thousand times.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is smug.
[SPEAKER_00]: A baobab tree.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always wanted to see one of those.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hammond, look at this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whoa!
[SPEAKER_00]: It is just about the most astonishing place I've ever been.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kind of witty there.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the sun set, we headed for the campsite.