[SPEAKER_03]: Look at that sun now, boys.
[SPEAKER_03]: Elephants, rally special stage, best comb-over I've ever seen.
[SPEAKER_03]: Everything's here.
[SPEAKER_04]: We camped by the river, and while James serviced his car, I hatched a plan.
[SPEAKER_00]: Jeremy.
[SPEAKER_04]: Jeremy.
Quick, come here.
Come here.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's the cow's head.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, well, it wasn't working in the boat.
I've had a better idea.
What?
[SPEAKER_04]: Ten.
[SPEAKER_04]: His ten?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Love your thinking.
What's that?
It was a hippo.
[SPEAKER_00]: What?
[SPEAKER_00]: Plugs.
[SPEAKER_00]: That sounded very close.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, my God, look at that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hippos spend all day in water and then they come out at night because... I can't remember why.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's useful.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, brilliant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Look, do you want to go out there with the hippopotamus?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or do you want to stay in here where the horse is sat?
[SPEAKER_04]: That's not a question that's ever been asked.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not a horse, either.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a cow.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hang on.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's my bag in James's tent.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is my tent!
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, man, get it out!
[SPEAKER_03]: Our starting point at the Zimbabwe border felt like it was in another time zone.
[SPEAKER_03]: But still, there were many miles of delta to cover, and our cars were in a really bad way.
[SPEAKER_03]: The bush mechanic we have on the team took two cubic feet of sand out of my carburettor last night and asked if I wouldn't mind driving a bit more slowly today.
[SPEAKER_03]: James, he's coming!
[SPEAKER_03]: Our ordinary second-hand road cars were getting more and more out of their depth.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is proper off-roading now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Men in camouflage trousers in Wales, who like murdering people at weekends, would say this was tough going.
[SPEAKER_04]: It was a whole... Oh!
[SPEAKER_04]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like iron.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think I've bent the steering back a bit.
[SPEAKER_04]: Wow!
[SPEAKER_01]: Wow, there is an elephant right there.
[SPEAKER_03]: A door there.
[SPEAKER_03]: That would stop an elephant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Soon our route was blocked by a river and what you're supposed to do is wade in to check the depth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jeremy made us drive on until he got bored.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here, now.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: I agree with him, for once, actually, because that reedy stuff must mean it's shallow.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's shallow where the reeds are, you fool.
[SPEAKER_03]: We'll just drive over to where the reeds are, then.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, but you've got to drive through the water to get there.
[SPEAKER_03]: We can't keep going.
[SPEAKER_03]: We've done 30 miles.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, I'm frustrated, but you can't just drive into a river because you're bored.
[SPEAKER_04]: I do a fair bit of off-roading, and I know enough that that's not the place to go across.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're wrong.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm going through here.
[SPEAKER_03]: Are you going to carry on?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, well, I will carry on if you're going to go through there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Keep your radio on.
[SPEAKER_04]: All right.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm going.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not doing a four-by-four.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so edging.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fan belts off.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fan belts off is a good idea.
[SPEAKER_03]: Cos it'll splash water into the distributors.
[SPEAKER_03]: James went first and I said I'd watch for crocodiles.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ooh, I say there's a ground hornbill over there.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's getting deeper.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ooh, hang on a minute.
[SPEAKER_01]: Permission to say cock.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's coming in!
[SPEAKER_02]: Thunderbird one to the rescue.
[SPEAKER_02]: Come on, I'm sinking by the bows.
[SPEAKER_02]: Coming.
[SPEAKER_02]: No!
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't help you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Come on.
[SPEAKER_02]: James, I'm in a low, slow sports car.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm going down.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's good.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes!
[SPEAKER_02]: I've got water coming into my car.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've got a wet bottom!
[SPEAKER_02]: We're through!
[SPEAKER_03]: Both our cars were flooded, but our guides weren't bothered at all.
[SPEAKER_03]: People of Surrey, if this happens to you, you get water in the footwell and you need to drain it out, you're going to need a hole.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the people of Botswana have a tip for you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Meanwhile...