[SPEAKER_00]: Guys, you know what we're driving through?
[SPEAKER_00]: Plants.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, this is a weed.
[SPEAKER_00]: It grows locally and it's hallucinogenic.
[SPEAKER_00]: What did you say?
[SPEAKER_00]: If any car was going to get stuck, we would have put money on the Lance here, but no.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right, mate?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_01]: Horn doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Clearly, I'd have to get myself out.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm going to make a rudimentary temporary road for my back wheel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank God.
[SPEAKER_02]: Eventually, we found a smoother track.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whoa!
[SPEAKER_02]: And I did a detailed analysis of the Lancia's conditioning.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sit-rep.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all broken.
[SPEAKER_00]: As darkness fell, we found the road to Mamm.
[SPEAKER_00]: But by this stage, even Oliver was suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't use my lights.
[SPEAKER_00]: Alternator's packed up all full of dirt and dust.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I put the lights on, I can have the lights, but not the engine, because it all dies.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I've actually got Jonathan, who brings all the cameras and does all that for us, in here with me, lighting me when I talk to you with the torch, which he then uses to light the road ahead when I'm not talking to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Finally, we rolled into Man.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which year was it made?
1981.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just driven all the way from Zimbabwe to here without going on a road.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like this?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Get out of the way of the pub.
[SPEAKER_02]: I shall move it for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you ask politely, I will move it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's his line.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are grown-ups, honestly.
[SPEAKER_00]: They do this a lot.
[SPEAKER_01]: We were now just over halfway, and amazingly, our cars were still running.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: The next day, in the centre of Maun, we got our next challenge.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Glittering Golden Envelope.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will drive your cars to Namibia through the Okavango Delta.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the really big wildlife place.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the Okavango, you will encounter many deadly animals, including lions, leopards, cheetahs, hyenas, wild dogs, hippos, black rhino and crocodile.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bird snakes, shield-nosed snakes, puff adders, boomslang, cape cobras, banded cobras, black mambas, black widows and thick-tailed scorpions.
[SPEAKER_02]: What about the honey badger?
[SPEAKER_02]: The what?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the least scary-sounding animal in the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: A honey badger does not kill you to eat you.
[SPEAKER_02]: It tears off your testicles.
[SPEAKER_00]: It does not!
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is it called a honey badger?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's why it's made it angry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why isn't it called the badger of death?
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to protect ourselves from the lions and the honey badgers, Jeremy and I would have to rebuild our cars.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because we'd left all the bits on the other side of the salt pans, we had to use whatever we could find.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did a lion eat this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Who do I see about the corrugated metal?
[SPEAKER_00]: I suppose I've had a practice, at least, with my lion drill.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, no, there's a lion coming.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, what shall I do?
[SPEAKER_00]: That.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oliver will protect me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I had nothing to do, I decided to irritate Jeremy.
[SPEAKER_02]: I want to go to that tarpaulin, then.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tarpaulin?
[SPEAKER_00]: Tarpaulin will defeat... Oh, no, it's well known, tarpaulin, for its almost military protective capabilities.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you often see people going into war zones draped in tarpaulin.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you put a new door on a car?
[SPEAKER_01]: Come and have a look.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll show you what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not sophisticated metalwork, this, but...
[SPEAKER_02]: I would like a tarpaulin roof for a Lancia Beta Coupe, 1981.
[SPEAKER_00]: We can.
[SPEAKER_00]: We can make anything here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you have any lion-proof tarpaulin?
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's got to be, like, this thick.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: One and a half metres by, say, one and a half metres.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you think of a lion door, it'd be about that big.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could you ignore him and make me that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because Mercedes were very popular in Africa, James soon found a spare door and boot lid for his car.
[SPEAKER_02]: And while he was looking for more bits, I hatched a plan.
[SPEAKER_02]: Look what I've got.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a cow's head.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, this will attract flies, which will make his life unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will also attract lions, tigers... He effectively becomes a burger van for driving.
[SPEAKER_00]: And to make sure the lions didn't miss,