[SPEAKER_02]: Hello, hello, and welcome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, as you know, the producers on this show like to give us challenges, specifically where they give us a very small amount of money and tell us to buy a used car.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then they set unbelievably hard tasks to do to see which one of us got the best deal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: This week, for a Top Gear special, they came up with a real humdinger.
[SPEAKER_00]: They gave each of us 1,500 quid and told us to go to Africa and buy a car.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there were just two conditions.
[SPEAKER_01]: It mustn't be four-wheel drive, and it mustn't be built in any way to go off-road.
[SPEAKER_01]: The meeting point was the border post between Zimbabwe and Botswana.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, for once, I was the first to arrive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, as you'd expect, I've done this properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: What I've got is a 1985 Mercedes-Benz 230e, a car that Africa absolutely adores, because it's comfortable, it's rugged, it's dependable, and frankly, if the other two have brought anything other than one of these along, they're idiots.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first idiot arrived.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you open the door?
[SPEAKER_01]: The handle's broken.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is a Lancia Beta.
[SPEAKER_02]: Coup, 1981.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only Lancia of any sort in the whole of Botswana.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's done 29,000 miles.
[SPEAKER_02]: One owner, is it?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the little old lady.
[SPEAKER_02]: And boy, had she ragged it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's normal, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: That fizzing?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the piece of cardboard for?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that for mopping up moisture?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, that's because the battery... Oh, it shorts on the bonnet?
[SPEAKER_02]: Shorts on the bonnet a bit.
[SPEAKER_02]: You've done well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you want a lift?
[SPEAKER_01]: We left the Lancia to cool down, because Hammond was arriving.
[SPEAKER_02]:  What the hell is that?
[SPEAKER_02]:  I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Could it be a Moskvitch?
[SPEAKER_02]:  It's an Opel.
[SPEAKER_02]:  Opel?
[SPEAKER_02]: And on the front it says Cadet.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah!
[SPEAKER_00]: What the hell have you done, man?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an Opel Cadet from 1963.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's the same age as... That's the same age as Nick.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, but it's much better Nick than you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was 1,200.
[SPEAKER_00]: I had much change with which to buy many beans.
[SPEAKER_00]: How much more simple can you get?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's got two moving parts and it's been here for 44 years.
[SPEAKER_02]: I love the speedo.
[SPEAKER_02]: I do like a horizontal speedo.
[SPEAKER_00]: I really do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Where's the engine?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hang on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's tiny.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you want to know about the power?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Forty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Forty horsepower.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, they did do a sport version with 48, but I didn't want anything too lairy.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've both been idiots.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Brilliantly interesting, brilliantly stylish, but stupid.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is mine stupid?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is yours?
[SPEAKER_00]: Anansi, you have been a bit thick.
[SPEAKER_02]: With the cars at the start line, it was time for our challenge.
[SPEAKER_02]: The people of Surrey think they need four-wheel drive cars because they live up a lane which sometimes has leaves on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will now attempt to prove them wrong by driving your two-wheel drive cars from here on Botswana's eastern border with Zimbabwe, which is there, 1,000 miles to its western border with Namibia.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's right across the spine of Africa.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm confident.
[SPEAKER_02]: I wasn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: We hadn't even started, and the Lancia was playing up.
[SPEAKER_02]: James chose not to wait.
[SPEAKER_02]: He may be mechanically confident, but he has just turned right, which is simply a bomb wing, which is where I should point out the BBC is not allowed.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry, sorry.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm going now.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Lancia wheezed into life and Hammond and I set off in pursuit.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you think of the cars that this inspired, it was Latin.