[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, that's a whopper.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a whole lion there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, under the seat.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, the smell will really... That'll be beautiful.
[SPEAKER_02]: We also attached a cowbell to the underside of his car.
[SPEAKER_02]: But while we were doing this, he was making merry with the paint.
[SPEAKER_02]: That afternoon, we left Man and headed north to the Okavango Delta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, my car now has been readied.
[SPEAKER_00]: As you can see, I have a wooden door here.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a gull-wing, so I can get in and out, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: God, this is like being in an allotment shed... on a very windy day.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the left, I have all the cans that were in the car for the last few days have been arranged, and Fiesta Resistance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Badgers, go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mad Jeremy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Police car.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can anybody else smell burning or is it my car?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it like a barbecue smell?
[SPEAKER_01]: As we neared the Okavango, the roads became rougher and rougher.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is where the Big Ben comes into its own, really, because it's got good ground clearance, nothing... Bloody hell.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is enough to shake the skulls from your bonnet, and nobody in the whole of human history has ever said that before.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just to summarise, viewers... As we went through the gates and into the game reserve, the road changed again, for the worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is new.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very soft sand.
[SPEAKER_01]: To stop our cars bogging down, we had to drive as fast as possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: We had ourselves another rally stage.
[SPEAKER_01]: Amazingly, even Jeremy had his work cut out keeping up with the Opel.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hammond's car just looks so composed.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm developing this irrational hatred of him and it.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is such a good game.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eventually, he was slowed down by a bridge over the river Kwai.
[SPEAKER_00]: The rally stage had taken its toll on one of the cars.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take a guess which one.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm in a car, which is even probably here, has got a throttle that's jammed wide open and I can't hold it on the brakes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hammond, move!
[SPEAKER_00]: You're going to have to go faster than I hit you.
[SPEAKER_00]: What?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, God!
[SPEAKER_02]: Thanks!
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, help yourself to my brakes, why not?
[SPEAKER_02]: I've lost a skull.
[SPEAKER_01]: Monkeys.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm sorry, I can't... I just hit the throttle.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's tick over.
[SPEAKER_00]: Look, my leg's not on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having blotched my throttle, we headed deeper into the Okavango.
[SPEAKER_00]: Front, 12 o'clock.
[SPEAKER_00]: One o'clock.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is where wildlife cameramen come to make a name for themselves with David Attenborough.
[SPEAKER_00]: But unfortunately, our film crew are best, really, with cars.
[SPEAKER_01]: A giraffe on the right.
[SPEAKER_01]: There.
[SPEAKER_00]: The big thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Little fluffy clouds.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have a programme called The Back End of an Animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Meet the boys to hire.
[SPEAKER_00]: This week on Too Late to Look.
[SPEAKER_02]: A moon on the left with animals with a baby on its back.
[SPEAKER_00]: To give our crew a chance, we stopped and discovered that we weren't much good at animals either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wow, look!
[SPEAKER_00]: Look!
[SPEAKER_00]: A hippo's head.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it is!
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's probably a whole hippo.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the rest of him is under the water.
[SPEAKER_02]: What does a hippo do just before it's about to attack?
[SPEAKER_00]: Opens its mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can open its jaw.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a thing it can do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, look!
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, look at that!
[SPEAKER_00]: They stop for a drink.
[SPEAKER_00]: using their noses to shovel water into their mouths.
[SPEAKER_02]: Jeremy, that's a rubbish commentary.
[SPEAKER_01]: James took over.
[SPEAKER_01]: That one's lifting its paw up a bit like a dog does.
[SPEAKER_01]: Paw.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hoof.
[SPEAKER_01]: Foot.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever you call it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hoof.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it on an elephant?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's amazing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a man over there with the best comb-over I have ever seen in my life.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is...
[SPEAKER_00]: He's got four partings as a result of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why don't... You're bald.
[SPEAKER_01]: Live with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oops, he called me back.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was looking through...