[SPEAKER_04]: Day two on the salt pans, and we'd been told that today our problem would not be mud, but dust.
[SPEAKER_04]: That meant James and I had to rethink our wardrobe solutions.
[SPEAKER_04]: I've teamed my koi with a bin liner.
[SPEAKER_04]: V-necked.
[SPEAKER_04]: The last time I wore one of these, I'd seen a clash.
[SPEAKER_04]: Frankly, I thought it was all a bit much.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, how bad could this dust be?
[SPEAKER_04]: My eyes!
[SPEAKER_00]: Crikey, I can't even see Jezza already.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Meanwhile, in my unmodified cadet... I'm going to adjust my quarter light a bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just an inch.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's better.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can feel the heat there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's nice.
[SPEAKER_00]: The kakai's come off.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hello?
[SPEAKER_04]: James and I made it through the dust with our lives considerably shortened.
[SPEAKER_04]: I've got consumption and TB.
[SPEAKER_04]: I've got every single 1920s disease.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then Lord Smug piped up.
[SPEAKER_02]: I had to close this at one point, just about that much, and then it pulls the air out and you just get fresh air through, it's nice.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know what it's like when someone punches you really hard in the middle of the face?
[SPEAKER_02]: I do, actually.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then the surface got even worse.
[SPEAKER_04]: It was like we were descending through the seven circles of hell.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'd assumed it'd be the salt that would kill the notoriously rust-prone Lancia, but it was the rough going.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even though it had now smoothed out again, the beater was in a bad way.
[SPEAKER_03]: I've gone.
[SPEAKER_03]: Are you conking out?
[SPEAKER_03]: I've got no power, no drive.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you remember what the man said, Jeremy?
[SPEAKER_03]: Breakdown and you... What is it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Have a nice time?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, die.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, that's loose.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's hot.
[SPEAKER_04]: It is a good job they cantered this engine over by 20 degrees, because that means it's more inaccessible than it would otherwise have been.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, my God, look at this.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've got to say, it has been nice, the piece.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, not having him around.
[SPEAKER_04]: I've checked the alternator, the spark plugs, the HT leads and the distributor cap.
[SPEAKER_04]: Poked around with the starter solenoid.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's been faults with all of them, but it still isn't going.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm not sure which I favour most here, certain death or that beetle.
Come off!
[SPEAKER_04]: I honestly believe it's had it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's my car on the crab.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's tracking Troentruve.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's worried about tracking, and look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: We knew that Jeremy would eventually catch us up, but what would he be driving?
[SPEAKER_01]: I can see something in the mirrors.
[SPEAKER_00]: Please let it be a beetle.
[SPEAKER_00]: I do hope it's a beetle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Please, please let it be a Beetle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Please let it be a Beetle.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm back!
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, Jeremy, well done.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm disappointed... Sorry, delighted.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not in a Beetle!
[SPEAKER_03]: Not a Beetle.
[SPEAKER_03]: A fully functioning Lancia Beetle Coupe.
[SPEAKER_03]: I just wanted the Beetle to pounce on you when you were straying behind.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm gutted.
[SPEAKER_03]: Shall we just sandwich him, James?
[SPEAKER_03]: No!
[SPEAKER_01]: With their convoy back on the road,