[SPEAKER_00]: And welcome!
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, as you know, the producers on this show like to give us challenges.
[SPEAKER_00]: Specifically, where they give us a very small amount of money and tell us to buy a used car.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then they set unbelievably hard tasks to do to see which one of us got the best deal.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: This week, for a Top Gear special, they came up with a real humdinger.
[SPEAKER_02]: They gave each of us 1,500 quid and told us to go to Africa and buy a car.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there were just two conditions.
[SPEAKER_01]: It mustn't be four-wheel drive and it mustn't be built in any way to go off-road.
[SPEAKER_01]: The meeting point was the border post between Zimbabwe and Botswana.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, for once, I was the first to arrive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, as you'd expect, I've done this properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: What I've got is a 1985 Mercedes-Benz 230e, a car that...