[SPEAKER_01]: Africa absolutely adores, because it's comfortable, it's rugged, it's dependable, and frankly, if the other two have brought anything other than one of these along, they're idiots.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first idiot arrived.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you open the door, because the handle's broken?
[SPEAKER_01]: It is a Lancia Beta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Coupe, 1981.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only Lancia of any sort in the whole of Botswana.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's done 29,000 miles.
[SPEAKER_01]: One owner, is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: A little old lady.
[SPEAKER_00]: And boy, had she ragged it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's normal, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: That fizzing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the piece of cardboard for?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that for mopping up moisture?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's because the battery... Oh, it shorts on the bonnet?
[SPEAKER_01]: Shorts on the bonnet a bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've done well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you want a lift?
[SPEAKER_01]: We left the Lancia to cool down because Hammond was arriving.
[SPEAKER_01]: What the hell is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.